Imagine I just hand you a box, and inside this box are, let's say, 16 billion microscopic components.
That is a lot of pieces to keep track of.
Right. It's completely overwhelming.
Yeah.
And then I tell you that to make this machine actually work, you have to wire all those components together.
Oh, and not just wire them up randomly, but with trillions of exact microscopic connections.
Exactly. Trillions.
By the way, the machine you're building in this scenario, it's the human neocortex. It's your brain.
Which is arguably the most complex object in the known universe.
Yeah, no pressure.
Right.
But here is the real catch for you. The instruction manual I give you to build this thing, the human genome, it's basically, well, it's mathematically vastly too small to actually specify where everything goes.
Yeah, it simply does not have enough storage capacity.
Right. There aren't enough bytes of data in the DNA to tell even a tiny fraction of those neurons how to wire up.
It's mathematically impossible.
But yet almost every single time the machine builds itself perfectly. So how would you even begin to solve that?
Well, it really forces us to confront this central paradox of biology, you know?
The blueprint thing, right.
Exactly. For decades, we've relied so heavily on this intuitive metaphor of the blueprint.
I mean, it makes sense on the surface.
It does. We treat DNA as this strict architectural diagram. We just assume there's a direct one-to-one mapping between the code in the genome and the final physical structure of the organism.
Right. Like gene A builds finger B.
Yeah. But if you actually run the numbers on information theory, the blueprint model just doesn't have the bandwidth. It can't explain the staggering complexity of what gets built in three-dimensional space.
Which brings us to our mission today.
Yeah.
We are going to completely and thoroughly dismantle that blueprint model.
We really are. We're taking a deep dive into a, frankly, groundbreaking 2026 theoretical framework.
Yeah. By a researcher named Flixian. The paper is titled How to Build a Neocortex, and it introduces this totally mind-bending concept called constraint geometry.
And the core of Flixian's framework, it just flips our entire understanding of biological development right on its head.
It's wild. It basically argues that biological complexity doesn't come from a master plan at all.
Right. It doesn't directly specify final outcomes. Instead, the complexity emerges dynamically.
Exactly. Dynamically, meaning it happens on the fly.
Exactly. Because biological systems are constantly reshaping the medium or the geometry, as Flixian calls it, through which their own signals travel.
Okay. Let's unpack this for you with a mental image. Picture trying to guide a million people to very specific seats in a massive stadium.
That sounds like a logistical nightmare.
Totally. Now, if you use the old blueprint model, you have to hand every single person a ticket with an exact seat number.
Right. And then you force them to navigate this static, unmoving maze of hallways.
Yeah. You are basically micromanaging every single route for a million people. It's impossible.
But constraint geometry says you just throw the assigned seating out the window.
You don't even give them tickets. As the crowd walks into the stadium, you dynamically open and close doors in the hallways as they move.
You're just altering the paths available to them in real time.
Exactly. The crowd naturally flows into the right configuration, simply based on the physical constraints you continuously impose on their movement.
That's a perfect way to visualize it. And Flixian builds this entire theoretical case by synthesizing four really recent, highly complex scientific papers.
Yeah. And over the course of this deep dive, we are going to connect some seriously weird stuff.
We're talking the veins of a Chinese money plant.
The squishy material phase shifts of a zebrafish embryo.
The evolutionary history of the human brain.
And finally, the actual way our memories are dynamically routed through our hippocampus.
Plants, fish, evolution, and memory. I mean, it sounds completely disparate.
It does sound like a random list.
But the logical through line here is going to completely change the way you look at the natural world.
It really is a paradigm shift.
Before we get into the leaves or the brains, though, we need to understand the structural foundation of this new theory.
Like, why is the blueprint metaphor mathematically failing us?
And what does this constraint geometry actually replace it with?
Right. So Flixian breaks this down into what the essay calls the four levels of explanation for biological organization.
And conflating these four levels is basically where traditional biology hit a brick wall, right?
Precisely. To understand any living system, Flixian argues we have to separate these conceptual layers.
So the first level is the state manifold.
State manifold. Okay. What does that mean in plain English?
In physics and math, a manifold is essentially the space of all possible configurations a system could theoretically take.
So if we're talking about a single cell.
The state manifold represents every possible combination of genes that could conceivably be turned on or off at the exact same time.
So it's basically the realm of absolute possibility.
Yes. The entire universe of things that could exist, even the totally chaotic or broken ones.
Got it. Okay. What's level two?
Level two is the admissibility structure. And this is the star of the show. This is what we're calling constraint geometry.
So how does that relate to the manifold?
Well, out of all those infinite possibilities in the state manifold, the admissibility structure is the dynamically evolving set of rules that determines which paths are currently open and which are closed.
It's the topology of the system at any given second.
Exactly.
So going back to the stadium analogy, the state manifold is every possible place a person could physically stand, including like on the ceiling or inside the plumbing.
Right. The absurd possibilities.
And level two, the admissibility structure, is the actual arrangement of open doors and walls at that specific minute.
Spot on. Then we have level three, which is stochastic dynamics.
Stochastic just means random, right?
Yeah. This is the noise, the random fluctuations, the tiny environmental inputs, the chemical Brownian motion that constantly bumps and nudges a system down one of those open paths instead of another.
Okay. So just the random messiness of life.
Mm-hmm.
And level four.
Finally, level four is the realized macroscopic structure. This is the final observable outcome.
The actual physical anatomy.
Exactly. The physical heart or the leaf or the brain that you can actually look at under a microscope.
Okay. So if I'm studying city traffic, the old blueprint model is obsessing over level four. It's trying to hard code the exact route of every single car from a top-down master plan.
Yeah. It's trying to trace the final structure directly back to a specific construction.
But constraint geometry says the city actually does all its work at level two.
Right. The city planners just control the traffic lights, the road closures, and the speed limits.
And the traffic itself, the final outcome we see at level four, it just flows naturally based on those constraints interacting with the random noise of level three.
That is exactly how Fliction frames it.
But here is my fundamental question with this.
If the final form isn't planned, if it's really just a result of shifting constraints and literal random noise, how is biology so insanely reliable?
That's the million-dollar question.
I mean, how do we almost always get a functioning, highly complex cortex if no one is explicitly drawing it?
The reliability comes precisely from the fact that evolution and development do almost all their explanatory work at level two, not level four.
Wait, really? So evolution doesn't care about the final shape?
Not directly, no. Evolution doesn't tinker with the final three-dimensional coordinates of a neuron. It tinkers with the admissibility rules.
Oh, I see.
Think about it mathematically. If you constrain the geometry of a system tightly enough, the random noise of level three actually ceases to be a problem.
Because it can't mess anything up.
Even better. It becomes the engine.
The system has nowhere to flow except toward a functioning organ because you've closed off all the doors that lead to a non-functioning state.
So the random noise just pushes it down the only safe hallway left.
Precisely.
The essay's main critique is that we've spent decades trying to mat final physical structures directly to genes, assuming the genes drew the map.
We're basically looking at the end product and assuming the DNA drew the final picture.
Right, but the DNA actually just built the bumpers on the bowling lane.
And the ball just bounced its way to the pins.
That makes so much sense.
We are essentially shifting our entire focus from the design of the object to the design of the environment that builds the object.
Exactly.
Now, to see how this reliability actually emerges without a central architect, we really have to move out of abstract theory.
Right.
We need to look at living tissue partitioning physical space.
How does a system build complex physical boundaries without knowing where the boundaries are supposed to go?
Which brings us to the first piece of the puzzle.
This is the 2026 paper by Zhang and colleagues.
Yes, the house plant.
They focused on a very specific plant, Pilea peperomeoids.
Commonly known as the Chinese money plant.
We are looking at the geometry of its leaves.
If you have one of these sitting on your desk right now, you might want to look really closely at it.
Yeah, we are trying to understand exactly how its veins form.
For the longest time, vascular patterning in plants was explained by something called Saks canalization hypothesis.
Okay, what's the basic idea there?
The idea is that a plant hormone called auxin flows from a source to a sink.
And as it flows, it creates this positive feedback loop that narrows the channel into a distinct vein.
So it's basically like a river carving a canyon over time.
Exactly like that.
A little bit of water finds a path of least resistance.
The flow erodes the path, making it deeper, which draws more water into that path.
Until you eventually have a deep, permanent, optimized channel.
Right.
And that mechanism perfectly explains open branching networks, like a tree trunk splitting into branches, or a river delta fanning out to the ocean.
But the Chinese money plant presents a massive geometric problem for that river analogy, doesn't it?
A huge problem.
It has what botanists call reticulate venation.
Which means the veins don't just branch out and end, right?
Right.
They form closed loops.
They create these interconnected polygonal enclosures across the entire surface of the leaf.
So if canalization is a river flowing from a high-pressure source to a low-pressure sink,
how do you explain a river that flows in a complete, perfect circle?
You can't.
You can't have a source to sink flow that perfectly closes a loop around a discrete point.
It defies logic.
The standard canalization model just completely collapses when confronted with closed loops.
It has defied biological explanation for decades.
So what did Zeng's team do differently?
They took a completely different approach.
They started mapping the position of these tiny structures on the leaf surface called hydathodes.
Wait, hydathodes?
What exactly are those?
They are essentially just secretarial water pores.
Okay, so like little sweat glands for the plant.
Basically, yes.
And what they noticed was wild.
They saw that in the Chinese money plant, the major vein networks form these closed polygons
that perfectly surround the individual hydathodes.
So the pore is always trapped right inside the loop.
Always.
And when they ran the spatial analysis, they proved that these veins perfectly match a mathematical
concept known as a Voronoi diagram.
Okay, a Voronoi diagram.
Let's try to visualize this conceptually for a second.
It's a fun one to picture.
Imagine you have a blank piece of paper and you just randomly drop 10 dots on it.
A Voronoi diagram divides that paper into 10 distinct shapes, one around each dot.
Right.
It tessellates the space.
And the defining rule of the geometry is this.
Every single point inside a shape is closer to its own dot than to any other dot on the paper.
Exactly.
So the boundary lines are drawn exactly, perfectly halfway between the dots.
And in the plant, the hydathodes act as the dots, the generator points of the tessellation.
And the leaf veins are the boundary lines.
And Zheng's team actually quantified this overlap to prove it wasn't just, you know, a loose visual resemblance.
I did the math.
They did.
They mathematically generated a pure Voronoi diagram based strictly on the coordinates of the hydathodes and then overlaid it onto the actual biological vein network.
To see how well they matched.
Right.
They calculated the Jaccard index, which is just a measure of the similarity and spatial overlap between two sets.
And I know they got a Jaccard index of 0.72.
Now, in the messy world of biology, where things are constantly growing and shifting and blowing in the wind, getting a 0.72 overlap with a pure mathematical construct is astronomically high.
It's basically a perfect match in biological terms.
It's high enough to confidently rule out the prevailing biological alternative, which was the KD tree model.
Was a KD tree model.
It's based on recursive spatial subdivision.
You take a space, draw a line to cut it in half, then draw lines to cut those halves in half, over and over.
Okay, it's a top-down hierarchical way of partitioning space.
Right, which fits really neatly with genetic instruction models.
Yeah, because a KD tree requires a set of instructions, like divide here, then turn 90 degrees, divide there.
But when they tested the KD tree model against the actual leaf veins, it only scored a 0.40.
Oh, wow.
So it was barely better than a random guess.
Exactly.
The leaf is not recursively branching based on a set of hierarchical instructions.
It is explicitly computing a Voronoi diagram.
Okay, but computing is a really strong word there because a leaf obviously doesn't know math.
Last time I checked, no.
There is no central nervous system calculating the equidistant boundary points between dozens of pores.
The DNA certainly doesn't have the coordinates for a Voronoi diagram.
No, it doesn't.
So how is the physical tissue doing this?
How do the cells know where the exact halfway point is without a blueprint?
This is our first real look at constraint geometry actually in action.
The mechanism is entirely local.
Local meaning it only cares about what's immediately next to it.
Yes.
The hydathodes do act as sources for the auxin hormone, but they don't produce highly polarized rushing transport like the river analogy.
So it's not a river.
What is it?
Instead, they emit weak, unpolarized concentration waves.
They basically broadcast the hormone outward equally in all directions, pulsing it into the surrounding tissue.
So instead of drawing a line, it's more like throwing a stone into a perfectly still pond and watching the circular ripples expand outward?
Exactly.
Now imagine throwing dozens of stones into the pond at the exact same time.
The auxin waves ripple outward.
And eventually they're going to hit each other.
Right.
Eventually a wave from one hydathode is going to collide with a wave from an adjacent hydathode.
They crash into each other.
You get wave interference.
When those two chemical waves meet, they produce a local concentration maximum, a literal ridge of hormone.
Oh, wow.
And that specific collision zone stabilizes the chemistry in those local cells, triggers vascular differentiation, and a physical vein begins to form right there.
Right where the waves crash.
Yes.
Because this is happening simultaneously between all adjacent hydathodes across the entire expanding leaf, the veins automatically form exactly halfway between the sources.
That is incredible.
The waves map out the precise boundary lines of a voronoid diagram simply through physical interference.
The plant doesn't know where the veins are supposed to go.
It just drops the hydathode, starts the waves, and the geometry solves itself.
It builds a physical wall exactly where the ripples crash.
The implication here for how biological networks optimize themselves is huge.
It really changes how we think about efficiency.
Because we usually assume biology is always optimizing for the shortest possible path, or the absolute fastest transport of water or nutrients.
But a voronoid diagram doesn't create the shortest path, does it?
No, it doesn't.
It optimizes for spatial balance.
It is an equilibrium partition geometry.
Meaning what, exactly?
The leaf is ensuring that every single sector of developmental territory has equal access to a pore without ever needing to measure the whole leaf.
It achieves global organization strictly through local, uncoordinated interaction.
Exactly.
But let me push back on this reliance on chemical waves for a second.
If your entire skeletal structure relies on delicate ripples crashing into each other at the exact right time, how does the plant survive the real world?
That's a very fair question.
I mean, what if there's a drought, or severe heat, or the leaf gets warped by a shadow and grows asymmetrically?
Wouldn't the timing of the waves get completely out of sync, and the entire vein system just collapse into chaos?
You are touching on the exact reason why a blueprint would fail, and why constraint geometry succeeds.
The Zhang paper explicitly tested this.
They tortured the plants.
Basically.
They subjected the plants to severe environmental stresses, shade, high temperatures, intense light.
The morphology of the leaves changed drastically.
It got all weird and warped.
Yeah, the hydathodes changed in size and spacing, but the Voronoi geometry held up flawlessly.
Oh.
If the shape warps, the math should warp.
Because the underlying mechanism, the local wave collision, is scale invariant.
It remains true regardless of the distance or the shape of the boundary.
Oh, I think I get it.
If the leaf grows asymmetrically and two hydathodes end up further apart...
The chemical waves simply travel a little further before they collide.
The halfway point shifts automatically.
The geometry adapts dynamically to the physical reality of the tissue.
Exactly.
If the plant relied on a fixed genetic blueprint, a warped leaf would literally tear the blueprint
apart.
Because the instructions would tell a vein to form where tissue no longer exists.
Right.
But because the system relies on dynamic local constraints, global coherence is maintained
effortlessly, no matter what environment it encounters.
The constraints create a system that is totally anti-fragile.
It's more resilient than a rigid plan could ever possibly be.
Far more resilient.
Okay, so we've seen how chemical waves can partition a flat two-dimensional canvas like
a leaf.
But what happens when the canvas itself is a three-dimensional, actively dividing, squishy
ball of cells?
That takes us out of the plant world and into the animal kingdom.
Yes.
The second paper Fliction synthesizes is by Autorino and colleagues from 2026, looking
at the early development of the zebrafish embryo.
And here we are going to see how chemical signals physically alter the actual material they
are traveling through.
The transition from the leaf to the embryo is basically the transition from a relatively
passive canvas to a canvas that actively fights back.
Yeah.
That's a great way to put it.
In classical developmental biology, we rely heavily on the concept of morphogen gradients.
The morphogen is just a chemical signal that tells embryonic cells what kind of tissue
they should eventually become.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And the standard model assumes that this chemical diffuses across a tissue and individual cells
essentially read their position based on the local concentration of the chemical.
So high concentration might tell a cell to become part of the head and low concentration
might tell it to become part of the tail.
Yes.
It's often called the French flag model.
It's like a speaker playing music in a large room.
The closer you are to the speaker, the louder the music is.
You know where you are in the room based on the volume.
Right.
But in that model, the air in the room is just a passive medium.
It just lets the sound pass through without changing.
But Autorino's work on the zebrafish blastoderm completely shatters that passive assumption.
It really does.
They studied a specific morphogen called nodal, which is critical for dictating early cell patterning
in the fish.
And they tracked it as it moved.
Yeah.
They tracked a nodal as it diffused through the early tissue of the embryo.
At this stage, the embryonic tissue is highly flea-like.
So the cells are loosely packed and just kind of sloshing around.
Exactly.
But they discovered that as nodal diffuses, it doesn't just pass through the cells like
sound through air.
It triggers a secondary pathway inside the cells it touches.
It's called the Wnt11F2 pathway, right?
Yes.
And what does that pathway actually do to the cells?
It dramatically increases cell-to-cell adhesion.
Okay.
The cells that come into contact with nodal suddenly start gripping onto their neighbors
really tightly.
So the signal is making the cells sticky.
Far more than sticky.
The signal pushes the entire tissue across a literal physical rigidity phase transition.
A phase transition.
Like water turning to ice.
Exactly like that.
It's a concept borrowed directly from physics, specifically rigidity percolation theory.
The tissue abruptly shifts from a fluid-like state, where things can diffuse easily, into
a solid-like state.
It forms a giant, rigid cluster of tissue.
It's literally like pouring water onto a dry sponge.
But as the water spreads, the chemical reaction turns the sponge into solid concrete.
That is the perfect analogy.
And this brings us to the profound feedback loop.
Right.
Because the concrete changes things.
As the tissue turns to concrete, as it rigidifies, its internal porosity collapses.
The microscopic gaps and channels between the cells seal up.
And what happens to our morphogen, our water, when the pores of the sponge seal up?
It gets trapped.
It physically cannot diffuse any further because the space between the cells is just gone.
The collapse of the tissue's porosity physically restricts the effective diffusivity of the nodal
ligand itself.
The signal literally builds a wall that stops its own progression.
It builds its own cage.
Because it can no longer spread out, the signal gets highly concentrated locally in the rigid
area.
And that massive localized spike in concentration forces the system to trigger its own genetic
inhibitor, a molecule called LEFTI, which shuts the whole process down safely.
The signal physically alters the medium it is traveling through.
And by altering the physical state of the medium, it dictates how far it can travel, which then
triggers its own off switch.
This is the definition of what Flixing calls an active medium.
Yes.
Positional information in an embryo isn't just a chemical gradient reading a passive map.
The map is co-constructed in real time by the chemical signal and the changing geometry of
the tissue it traverses.
Beautifully said.
But I have to ask, correlation isn't causation.
How do we know the tissue hardening is actually what stops the signal?
You're wondering if it's just a coincidence.
Yeah.
Maybe the tissue is just naturally hardening on its own developmental clock at the exact
same moment the signal happens to run out of steam.
The Autorino team anticipated that exact skepticism, and they proved the causal link with one of
the most elegant experiments in recent biology.
The optogenetic rescue.
I love this part.
It's brilliant.
First, they took mutant zebrafish embryos that had a broken Wendt 11F2 pathway.
These embryos genetically could not increase cell adhesion, so their tissue stayed fluid.
The sponge never turned to concrete.
Correct.
And just as the constraint geometry framework predicted, in those fluid mutants, the nodal
signal diffused wildly out of control.
It just kept going.
It traveled way too far, the gradient flattened out, and the patterning was completely ruined.
Because there was no physical wall to stop it.
Exactly.
Then came the optogenetics.
They used light-activated proteins inserted into those same mutant embryos.
Light-activated proteins.
Yeah.
By shining a highly targeted laser on the fluid tissue, they manually forced the cells
to contract and rigidify.
They didn't touch the chemical signaling pathways.
Nope.
They didn't add more nodal or lefty.
They simply used light to manually restore the physical geometry of the tissue.
They manually turned the sponge to concrete with a laser.
Wow.
And what happened to the chemical signal?
It completely rescued the normal nodal distribution.
Wow.
The exact spatial and temporal dynamics of the morphogen gradient returned to wild-type levels,
the tissue patterned normally.
So you can break the chemical gradient by removing the physical geometry, and you can
fix the chemical gradient by restoring the physical geometry.
It is absolute proof that the material state of the tissue is causally upstream of the chemical
signal.
That is mind-blowing.
The geometry controls the chemistry, not the other way around.
It flips the whole script.
Now, the flixion essay mentions that this phase transition in the fish happens exactly
at a critical point.
I know criticality is a massive concept in complex systems physics.
It's essential here.
The paper notes the transition happens when cells reach an average of about four cell-to-cell
contacts.
Why does the tissue hover right on this edge?
Why not just be definitely fluid early on and definitely solid later?
Well, a critical point in physics is a regime where a system is poised on the razor's edge
between two phases.
Like water exactly at zero degrees Celsius.
Exactly.
Poised to perfectly between forming ice crystals and melting into liquid.
In the zebrafish blastoderm, hovering at that critical threshold of four cell contacts
maximizes the system's sensitivity to instruction.
How does being on the edge make it more sensitive?
If the embryonic tissue was deep in the fluid phase, adding a tiny bit of nodal wouldn't
change its bulk properties much.
It would just wash away.
Right.
It would just dissipate.
And if it was already deep in the solid phase, the nodal couldn't mold it at all.
It's already stuck.
Okay.
Yeah, it makes sense.
By poising the entire tissue network exactly at criticality, a microscopic chemical input,
a tiny localized whisper of nodal, can cascade through the network and cause massive tissue-wide
structural reorganization.
So the tissue acts as an evolutionary amplifier.
Yes.
It maximizes the efficiency of the signaling, allowing massive transformations with minimal
energetic input.
The tissue is basically a loaded spring, just waiting for the tiniest molecular nudge to
snap into an entirely new architectural shape.
That's a great visual.
So we've seen how dynamic constraints operate in physical space, using waves to build boundaries
and leaves, and using chemical signals to turn squishy tissue into rigid barriers in
fish.
Now we are going to make a massive jump.
Yes, we are.
We are moving up the evolutionary ladder to the human neocortex.
And here, the geometry we were talking about isn't physical space or concrete-like tissue.
No.
The constraints are temporal and regulatory.
We shift our focus to the 2026 paper by Javid and colleagues.
They set out to answer a question that has plagued neuroscience and evolutionary biology for
a century.
Which is, why is the human cortex so phenomenally more complex, so much thicker, and packed with
so many more neurons per square millimeter than a mouse's cortex?
Right.
And if you approach this with the old blueprint model, the intuitive answer seems obvious.
Yeah.
If the human brain is structurally a skyscraper and the mouse brain is a bungalow, the human
genome must contain a bunch of complex architectural blueprints that the mouse doesn't have.
We must have evolved new smart genes to build the extra floors.
That is the naive expectation dictated by genetic determinism.
But the Javid paper demonstrates that this expectation is completely, fundamentally wrong.
It's not new genes.
Human and mouse cortical progenitors, the stem cells that actually build the brain during
embryonic development, they share the exact same genetic coordinate system.
The molecular tools are almost entirely conserved.
Yes.
So if a human and a mouse have the exact same tool built, how do we end up building a skyscraper?
The difference lies entirely in accessibility.
Accessibility.
Let's dig into that.
Flixion frames this by returning to our first level of explanation, the state manifold.
Right.
The map of all possibilities.
Imagine a massively high-dimensional map of every possible genetic state a mammalian cell
could be in, both the mouse and the human possess this exact same vast map.
But during development, they take different paths through it.
Exactly.
The rules governing which paths are open, at what times the constraint geometry of the
genome itself, is what differs.
I need to ground this in the biology, though.
How does a gene actually become accessible or inaccessible?
We aren't talking about doors in a hallway anymore.
No.
We are talking about physical constraints on the DNA itself.
Okay.
Physically how?
DNA is not just a loose string floating around in the nucleus.
It is tightly spooled around proteins called histones, forming this dense structure called
chromatin.
Like thread around a school.
Right.
And if a section of DNA is tightly wound up, the cellular machinery literally cannot physically
reach it to read the gene.
It is locked.
Inaccessible.
So to turn a gene on, regulatory molecules have to physically unspool that specific section
of DNA opening the geometric structure so it can be read.
Exactly.
So accessibility is a literal physical geometry problem at the molecular level.
Give me an example from the paper.
What specific tool are the human and the mouse using differently?
The prime example in the Javid paper is a gene called J-U-N-B.
J-U-N-B.
Okay.
It is a transcription factor, which is a highly conserved piece of molecular machinery.
The protein it produces is essentially identical in humans and mice.
But its accessibility landscape is radically different.
Completely different.
In mice, the J-U-N-B gene only unschools as it only becomes accessible very late in the
developmental process.
Late in the game.
Right.
It primarily turns on in postmetodic mature neurons.
It's an end-stage tool for the mouse.
It basically helps polish the finished bungalow.
Precisely.
But in humans, the constraint geometry is shifted.
J-U-N-B unspools and becomes accessible very early in development.
How early?
It activates in early radial glia, which are the foundational stem cells of the entire brain.
Oh, wow.
Because it turns on early, its function changes entirely in context.
It massively extends the period of cell proliferation.
So it keeps the stem cells dividing.
Yes.
Multiplying their numbers exponentially long before they finally commit to maturing into
neurons.
The essay refers to this shifting of developmental windows as heterocrony.
Heterocrony is the evolutionary strategy of changing the timing of developmental events
without changing the events themselves.
By simply shifting, when J-U-N-B becomes accessible, altering the temporal constraint geometry,
the human brain produces millions more precursor cells before the developmental window finally
closes.
That's the secret to the skyscraper.
Here is where the J of paper gets truly incredible to me.
They didn't just observe this difference.
They manipulated it.
They did.
They wanted to see if they could mess with the accessibility in a living animal.
So they did an experiment with a gene called IRF1.
IRF1 acts like the upstream boss.
It's the regulatory key that physically unspools the chromatin and unlocks the J-U-N-B program.
In normal mouse development, IRF1 isn't active early on, so the J-U-N-B gene stays coiled
up and locked away.
Right.
But JVED's team essentially hacked the mouse genome.
They experimentally activated IRF1 in the early cortical tissue of a mouse embryo.
They turned the boss on early.
And the results were profound.
When they forced IRF1 to activate early, the J-U-N-B gene unspooled in the early mouse
progenitors.
And what happened?
Suddenly, the mouse tissue began exhibiting latent human-like cortical development.
Are you serious?
Totally.
The progenitor cells persisted much longer.
They divided more frequently.
The entire developmental trajectory shifted away from the mouse bungalow and began laying
the foundation for the human skyscraper.
That is staggering to think about.
It means the human program wasn't missing in the mouse.
Not at all.
It wasn't something humans invented millions of years later.
The program was already installed in the mouse genome.
It was just hidden behind a regulatory firewall.
The molecular machinery to execute a radically more complex cortex was poised, existing in the
state manifold.
But it was geometrically inaccessible during that specific time window.
It's exactly like buying the standard version of a video game on a disc.
Oh, I like this analogy.
You think you only bought the base game, but the actual code for the massive 100-hour expansion
pack is secretly already right there on the disc.
Right.
You just can't play it yet.
You don't need to download new code.
You just need the regulatory unlock key, in this case, IRF1, to gain access to it.
That is a perfect way to describe heterocrony.
But this raises a huge evolutionary question for me.
If the mouse has this latent, highly complex potential just sitting there on its hard drive,
why keep it hidden?
Evolution is weird like that.
Does keeping it latent serve some biological purpose?
Or is it just leftover evolutionary baggage from some distant ancestor?
That question cuts to the heart of how evolution actually innovates.
Evolution very rarely invents a massive new biological structure from scratch.
Because that would require a lot of lucky mutations.
Exactly.
Doing so requires random mutations, and random mutations in a highly complex interconnected
system almost always break the system.
Instead, evolution plays with the constraints.
It searches for what Fliction calls evolutionary soft spots.
Soft spots.
Yeah.
Meaning developmental stages that are safe to mess with.
Exactly.
Think about a terminal, mature neuron.
It is under intense functional selection.
Because it's doing a specific job right now.
Right.
If you mutate mature neuron, the animal's brain misfires, it can't run from a predator,
and it dies.
The constraints there are rigid.
But the intermediate progenitor cells, the cells halfway between a stem cell and a mature
neuron, are under much weaker immediate functional constraints.
Evolution can safely accumulate regulatory changes in these soft spots.
It can shift timing, open new accessibility pathways, and stretch out developmental windows without immediately breaking the final life-or-death output.
So the mouse isn't carrying the human program as useless baggage.
Rather, the fundamental mammalian genomic manifold is incredibly vast.
Both the mouse and the human represent different accessibility paths carved through that same vast landscape of potential.
Evolution doesn't write new code.
It just dynamically shifts the boundaries of what code can be accessed.
That's the beauty of it.
That is a brilliant way to look at our own history.
We are just a different geometric path through the same ancient map.
We really are.
So we've seen how altering accessibility, opening the right genetic doors at the right time, builds the immensely complex hardware of the human brain.
But how does that brain actually process information moment to moment once it is fully built?
How do we actually think?
That leads us to the fourth and final paper, which argues that the brain uses the exact same geometry-altering tricks to route our actual real-time thoughts.
We move from the slow timescale of evolutionary development to the millisecond timescale of cognition.
The 2026 paper by Gonzalez et al. focuses on the hippocampal retrosplenial circuit.
Okay, let's break that circuit down.
This is a vital neural pathway that moves information from the CA3 region of the hippocampus into the CA1 region and then out to the retrosplenial cortex, or RSC.
And what does this circuit do?
This circuit is absolutely critical for memory formation and spatial navigation.
Normally, when we talk about how the brain communicates, we default to anatomical blueprints again, right?
We talk about the connectome.
The physical wiring diagram.
The assumption is that if neurons in region A have long physical axons that plug into neurons in region B, they communicate.
If they are plugged in, information flows.
If they aren't, it doesn't.
It's a very static telephone wire view of the brain.
The physical connectome is the structural hardware, and it is important.
But Gonzalez's team demonstrated that the static wiring diagram is profoundly incomplete.
How so?
Two regions can be physically connected with thousands of synapses, but if they're population dynamics, the synchronized rhythmic firing patterns of the thousands of neurons are not properly aligned, absolutely no information transfers between them.
None.
The brain routes information using dynamic, low-dimensional communication subspaces.
Okay.
We need to translate low-dimensional communication subspaces into something we can visualize.
Let's use a musical analogy.
Imagine a massive choir consisting of 10,000 singers.
Okay.
A huge choir.
The physical choir on the stage represents the anatomy, the connectome.
But if the conductor wants to send a very specific, subtle emotional message, they don't have all 10,000 people scream at once.
It would just be noise.
Exactly.
They might only need the altos and a few specific sopranos to sing a complex harmonic progression while everyone else stays quiet or hums softly in the background.
And that specific, coordinated pattern of activity, ignoring the rest of the noise, is a subspace.
Yes.
The Gonzalez researchers used advanced mathematical tools, specifically partial canonical correlation analysis, to sitch through the chaotic noise of millions of firing neurons and isolate these exact harmonic combinations that transmit specific memories from CA1 to its targets.
It's finding the hidden jazz band inside the massive orchestra.
I like that.
And the massive finding of this paper, the thing that really shifts the paradigm of neuroscience, is a phenomenon they observed called subspace rotation.
Yes, subspace rotation.
What is the middleman, the CA1 region, actually doing with these subspaces?
CA1 receives the memory input from CA3, and it has to send the output to the rest of the brain via the RSC.
The blueprint model assumes CA1 acts like a copper wire, just passively passing the message along.
But Gonzalez found that CA1 actively transforms the geometry of the message.
Transforms it how?
The pattern of neurons in CA1 that is actively listening to CA3 is fundamentally different from the pattern of neurons that is speaking to the RSC.
But they are the exact same physical pool of neurons, right?
The anatomy hasn't changed.
The physical neurons are the exact same.
The neuronal membership heavily overlaps.
But the pattern of their participation, the mathematical weighting of their firing, rotates.
It rotates.
In the high-dimensional geometry of neural activity, the input subspace and the output subspace are almost entirely orthogonal to each other.
They are pushed nearly 90 degrees apart.
Let's use the choir analogy again to make this really concrete.
Sure.
It's the exact same group of musicians standing on the stage in CA1.
When they look over their left shoulders to listen to the CA3 conductor, they coordinate their instruments to play a complex improvisational jazz piece.
That is the input subspace.
Okay.
Then, without ever leaving the stage, without unplugging a single instrument, they look over their right shoulders toward the RSC audience,
and they completely reorganize their coordination to play a rigid classical symphony.
The output subspace.
The musicians never move, the physical wiring of the brain never changes, but they dynamically rotate their coordination to transform the information.
That is a perfect visualization.
The implication goes even further because Gonzales asked the critical computational question.
Is this rotation just an epiphenomenon?
Meaning, is it just a quirky mathematical accident of how biological networks fire, or is it computationally necessary for the brain to function?
Does the rotation actually do work?
To test this, they built an artificial recurrent neural network, an AI model, and tasked it with replicating this CA3 to RSC routing function.
Okay, so they simulated it.
First, they trained the AI normally, allowing it to naturally rotate its subspaces just like the biological brain does.
The AI learned the routing task perfectly and efficiently.
And then they actively interfered with the geometry.
They froze the subspaces in the AI.
They mathematically forced the input and output layers to stay perfectly aligned, preventing any orthogonal rotation, while still allowing the individual connection ways to try and learn the task.
And what happened to the AI?
The network's performance absolutely tanked.
The learning was profoundly impaired.
So the rotation is not an accident.
It is computationally load-bearing.
It is absolutely essential.
Why is forcing the message to turn 90 degrees computationally necessary?
What disaster happens if the input and output just face the same way?
Contextual interference.
It allows CA1 to route information selectively based on context, without having to physically rewire the brain.
Selective routing.
If the input and output were perfectly aligned, any noise, any stray thought, or any irrelevant memory from CI3 would blast straight through CA1 and corrupt the cortex.
Oh, so it acts like a filter.
By rotating the subspace orthogonally, CA1 ensures the information is transformed and controlled.
It can selectively route a memory of a dangerous maze to the cortex when the mouse is actually navigating the maze,
and completely decouple that pathway when the mouse is eating, simply by rotating the geometry of the communication so the signal no longer aligns with the receiver.
Speaking of decoupling, the data in this paper regarding sleep is absolutely fascinating.
What happens to these geometric spaces when the animal goes to sleep and starts dreaming?
The researchers analyzed the animal's brain during non-REM sleep ripples,
which is the period when the brain rapidly replays memories from the day to learn them.
Right, consolidating memories.
They discovered a brilliant division of labor based on geometry.
The CA1-CA3 subspace, the internal memory connection within the hippocampus, is highly plastic during sleep.
Meaning it changes a lot.
Yes.
Its geometry is constantly shifting and updating as it learns the new mazes from that day.
But the CA1-RSE subspace, the output channel to the deep cortex, remains rock-stable.
It does not fluctuate.
So the brain is protecting the deep, long-term memories stored in the cortex from being accidentally overwritten by the chaotic, fast-paced learning happening inside the hippocampus.
It achieves cognitive flexibility, the ability to learn new things rapidly while perfectly protecting old things using the exact same anatomical hardware.
It does this simply by varying the communication geometry over time.
Exactly.
I have to ask, what does this mean for the multi-billion dollar efforts to map the human connectome?
It certainly complicates things.
If we are spending decades trying to map the physical wiring of every single neuron, but the subspaces can just dynamically rotate and sever communication without touching the wires,
is mapping the anatomy ultimately a dead end?
It is not a dead end, but it's fundamentally incomplete.
The anatomical connectome sets the absolute outer boundary of what is geometrically possible.
It builds the physical stadium.
But the effective communication geometry, the actual real-time routing of information, is a time-varying projection structure.
So knowing the roads isn't enough.
Having a map of the physical roads in a city does not tell you anything about the traffic patterns on a Tuesday morning.
If we want to understand how a thought actually moves through the brain, we cannot just look at the static roads.
We have to map the dynamic constraints.
Okay.
We have covered a massive amount of conceptual ground here.
From the closed-loop physical veins of a money plant, to the rigid material phase transitions of a fish embryo.
To the latent genetic firewalls of mammalian evolution.
To the dynamically rotating musical choirs of our memory circuits.
It is time to bring this all together under Fliction's Grand Synthesis.
We are looking for the unified theory of active media.
What is the single thread that connects a leaf to human memory?
The unifying thread lies in the mathematical heart of Fliction's framework.
The concept of the evolving propagation kernel.
A propagation kernel? What is that?
In physics, a kernel simply describes how a signal originating at point A influences point B, given the current geometry of the intervening space.
Okay, so like a signal traveling through a wire.
Right. In a traditional engineered system, like a fiber optic cable, the kernel is fixed.
A pulse of light enters the cable, travels through it, and exits.
And the physical cable itself does not care that the light went through it. Its geometry remains unchanged.
It is a totally passive medium. The wire is completely indifferent to the electricity or light it carries.
But Fliction's Grand Synthesis is that biological systems are never passive.
They are self-modifying propagation media.
The defining feature of life, across all scales, is profound reflexivity.
In biology, the signal always modifies the medium it travels through.
Let's track that reflexivity through all four of our examples to really lock this in.
Let's do it.
In the Palaia leaf, the unpolarized auxin wave is the signal.
But as it propagates and collides, it triggers cell differentiation that creates physical, rigid vein boundaries.
The signal literally builds the physical walls that will permanently constrain all future chemical signals.
The signal modifies the medium. In the zebrafish embryo, the nodal morphogen is the signal.
But as it diffuses, it triggers the surrounding tissue to rigidify into a concrete-like state and lose its porosity.
Which physically traps the nodal from diffusing any further.
The signal modifies the medium.
In the cortical progenitors building the human brain, transcription factors like IRF1 are the signal.
But their activation physically unspools the chromatin.
Altering the accessibility landscape of the entire genome, which fundamentally changes which future genes, like J-U-N-B, can even be accessed by the cell.
The signal modifies the medium.
And finally, in the hippocampus, the neural activity from CA3 is the signal.
But that very activity drives the orthogonal rotation of the communication subspaces.
Dynamically altering the routing geometry for all future thoughts sent to the rest of the cortex.
It is everywhere.
At every scale of life, every signal changes the geometry that dictates how future signals will move.
It is a beautiful, unified concept.
But I want to play devil's advocate for a second, because this raises a terrifying theoretical question.
Oh, what's that?
If absolutely every signal permanently alters the medium it travels through, how does life not just spiral into a chaotic, endless feedback loop?
Ah, I see what you mean.
What stops the active medium from modifying itself into oblivion?
If the sponge turns to concrete to stop the water, you can't use the sponge ever again.
This is the genius of evolution operating at level 2, the constraint level.
The self-modification is not wild or unconstrained.
It is inherently self-limiting.
Self-limiting, like the fish tissue.
Yes.
The tissue rigidity in the fish stops the nodal signal, which immediately stops the rigidification process.
The system naturally settles into a stable equilibrium.
Okay, so biological development is not a chaotic spiral.
As Flexion elegantly defines it, development is controlled constraint reorganization.
Biological systems move through a precise sequence of quasi-stable constraint geometries.
So each stage sets up the next.
Each signal collapses the current geometry, which perfectly poises the system for the next necessary geometry until the mature, stable organ is fully formed.
This is exactly why biological systems completely resist being understood through static snapshots.
You cannot freeze a cell or a squishy embryo tissue or a living brain, take a picture of it, and claim to fully understand how it works.
Because its entire historical sequence of signals has invisibly, fundamentally altered its future constraints.
The blueprint metaphor is a lie, because the ink is constantly rewriting the paper it's printed on.
That's beautifully said.
A blueprint captures a single snapshot in time, but it completely misses the hidden dynamics of the medium in which that state is embedded.
And if you only study the snapshot, you will never understand the machine.
Never.
Let's do a rapid-fire summary, because my brain is officially full and we've covered a staggering amount of science.
It has been a lot.
We started by dismantling the 20th century idea of the biological blueprint.
We saw how a simple houseplant builds perfect Voronoi vein networks, not with a master plan, but by letting chemical waves crash into each other to find spatial balance.
Beautiful physical math.
We saw how a zebrafish embryo physically turns its own liquid tissue into rigid concrete, just to trap and control its own chemical signal.
Self-modifying media.
We saw how the massive human neocortex isn't built with entirely new smart genes, but by unlocking latent software already present in our mammalian ancestors through altered timing.
Genomic constraint geometry.
And finally, we saw how our memories are dynamically routed through the brain by rotating communication subspaces, like musicians shifting their coordination without ever leaving the stage.
I really want to thank you for holding on through this incredible, mind-expanding deep dive into the geometry of life.
It is a massive conceptual shift to move from blueprints to constraints.
But the predictive consequences of this framework are where the science gets truly exciting.
Oh, for sure.
Affliction leaves the reader with a paradigm-shifting idea for the future, particularly for the future of medicine.
Think about how we approach medicine today.
Currently, if we want to cure a complex disease, we almost always default to attacking the bad signals.
We look for a rogue inflammatory protein or a misfiring cluster of neurons or an overactive chemical pathway.
And we spend billions of dollars inventing a highly specific drug to block that signal downstream.
But if friction's constraint geometry framework is right, we are approaching the problem backwards.
Because the signal isn't the root issue.
In complex systems, upstream geometry always beats downstream signals.
Think about the implications of that.
What if the future of medicine isn't spending a decade inventing a new chemical hammer to smash a bad signal?
What if the future is simply gently tweaking the constraint geometry of the tissue itself?
What if instead of fighting the rogue chemical, we just slightly shift the physical permeability of the cells or gently rotate the communication subspace of a neural circuit out of alignment?
Effectively closing the door so the disease simply loses its physical ability to propagate.
It is the difference between trying to catch every single speeding car in a massive city versus simply changing the timing of the red lights so that speeding becomes geometrically impossible.
That is a staggering thought to end on.
The power isn't in the signal.
The ultimate power is in the medium.
So later today, go look at a leaf on a house plant.
Think about the hidden waves crashing inside it.
Or better yet, picture your own thoughts and the invisible rotating geometry that is allowing you to understand these concepts right now.
Until the next deep dive, keep questioning the blueprint.